<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true report and description of the taking of the iland and towne of S. Maries by a shippe of Amsterdam, and foure English pinnasses. 1599. Translated out of Dutch into English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11332</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21591</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102612</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838384</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838384</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2760</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11332)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2760)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1116:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true report and description of the taking of the iland and towne of S. Maries by a shippe of Amsterdam, and foure English pinnasses. 1599. Translated out of Dutch into English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8]p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by [J. Windet for] Iohn Wolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Actural printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Publisher's device (McKerrow 242) on title page.</note>
                  <note>A translation from the original Dutch.</note>
                  <note>At end: "Pervsed by me Garret Iohnson Cater.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>[Santa Maria(Azores)] --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Elizabeth, 1558-1603 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:2760:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2760:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRVE REPORT AND DESCRIPTION of the taking of the Iland and Towne of <hi>S. Maries,</hi> by a Shippe of <hi>Amſterdam, and foure Engliſh Pinnaſſes.</hi> 1599.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of Dutch into Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>embellished fleur de lis</figDesc>
               <head>VBIQVE FLORET</head>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Imprinted by <hi>Iohn Wolfe.</hi> 1600.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2760:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2760:2"/>
            <head>A true report and Deſcription of the taking of the Iland and Towne of S. Maries, by a ſhip of Amſterdam and foure Engliſh Pinnaſſes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that the great and mightie fleet, ſet forth and furniſhed by the vnited Prouinces (in the yeare of our Lord 1599.) againſt the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> and his countries, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the conduct and command of the noble Lord <hi>Peter van Does,</hi> Admirall and Generall of the ſame, had ſet ſaile, and put themſelues forwards on their no leſſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant then ſucceſfull voyage (which God with his omnipotent hand alwaies vouchſafeth to guide and protect in all their lawfull attemptes:) it ſo chanced, that vpon the 10. of Iune, there ſtrayed from the fleete, a ſhip of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> wherein was Captaine <hi>Garret Iohnſon Cater,</hi> who in croſſing to and fro, to recouer a ſight of the fleet, for about the ſpace of three weekes, happened vpon the firſt of Iuly to diſcrie neere vnto the Iland of Saint <hi>Mary</hi> foure ſmall ſailes, which afterwards he perceiued to be foure ſmall Engliſh Pinnaſſes, whereof the biggeſt was of the burthen of thirtie laſtes, the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer about ſeauen laſtes, and the other two accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. Being all theſe four Pinnaſſes together furniſhed with nine caſt pieces, and could make out amongſt them one hundred men, (when that they
<pb facs="tcp:2760:3"/> knew them to be all friends, and that the Captains had beene aboard one of the other) after their mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all greetings and welcomes vſed at ſea, the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Captaines gaue Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>taine <hi>Cater</hi> intelligence, how that they lay in waite for a barke lying vnder <hi>S. Maries</hi> Iland, which they ſaid was rich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y laden, contayning a great treaſure, and that with his aid and help they might eaſily take her. Whereupon the ſaid <hi>Cater</hi> promiſed them his good helpe, and furtherance to fetch the barke from the ſhoare, if ſo it were, that by his aſſiſtance they might take her: but it was told him by the Captaine of the greater Pinnaſſe that it would be impoſſible to take the barke, without that firſt they tooke the Iland it ſelfe. Whereupon after deliberation taken with them (being able to furniſh out in al, nine ſcore men, which the ſaid Captaine ſaid would ſuffice to take the Iland) they reſolued to aſſault the ſame with their men. And hauing made the ſaide Captaine <hi>Cater</hi> their Admirall, they altogether bended their courſe towardes the Iland, and the ſame day en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred vnder the towne, preparing themſelues to giue the aſſault the next day.</p>
            <p>The ſecond of Iuly, being the viſitation of the bleſſed virg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>Marie,</hi> they ſhot very ſtrongly with foure gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at peeces out of Captaine <hi>Caters</hi> ſhip vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the towne of <hi>S. Marie:</hi> meane while the men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owed a ſhore, being all well appointed and prepared to skirmiſh, taking their courſe Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to the Iland, to fal vpon the ſame in the low ground, but they could not doe it, by reaſon of the
<pb facs="tcp:2760:3"/> great number of the inhabitantes vpon the ſhoare, which eaſily might haue hindered their landing. Wherefore Captaine <hi>Cater</hi> after due conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thought it requiſite to ſende two of the Engliſh pinnaſſes, with eight or ten men towards the weſt ſide of the ſaid Iland, the which with plying vp and downe, ſhould ſeeme to aſſault the Iland on that ſide, himſelfe going alſo in his boate, with ſome of his men, rowing towards the Weſt ſide of the Iland: whereupon they were ſhot at by ſome Spaniſh ſoldiers with Muſkets, which lay there vpon the flat land, and afterwardes the ſame day they ſhot mightily with a great peece vpon the pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes, all which was done to that ende, that the ſoldiers which were occupied on the Weſt ſide of the Iland, ſhould not withdraw themſelues to the Eaſt ſide thereof to reſiſt their aſſault there: which otherwiſe without doubt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y would haue done.</p>
            <p>Our men now being landed in the Eaſt part of the Iland, after a ſmall skirmiſh and little trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, (by Gods help) wonne the Iland: for the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niardes on the Eaſt ſide being aſſaulted ſuddenly and vnlooked for, fled immediately: ſo that our men tooke not onely the aboue named barke, but alſo had the whole Iland and the Towne to their will and diſpoſition.</p>
            <p>Which done, the ſaid Captaine <hi>Cater</hi> by aduiſe of the Engliſh Captaines, ſet a ranſome on the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, commanding the chiefe inhabitants thereof to bring them a certaine ſumme of Duckets.</p>
            <p>Vpon the 4. of Iuly they forſooke the Iland a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb facs="tcp:2760:4"/> becauſe there was no good roade to ride in, as alſo becauſe that the Weſterly winde began to riſe ſtrongly from the ſhore, ſo that they ſhould haue beene in ſome perill if they had ſtayed.</p>
            <p>Thus was the Ilande and Towne of S. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> wonne and taken, after they had lyen there three daies.</p>
            <p>They might wel haue kept the ſame, if they had thought it to haue beene any thing aduantagious, or profitable for them.</p>
            <p>The chiefe of the Iland being by them deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded what the reaſon was that ſo lightly they yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Iland: aunſwered, that they knew God was diſpleaſed with them, that hee would puniſh them for their ſins, and that therfore they thought it in vaine to reſiſt.</p>
            <p>To the Almightie God be infinit praiſes for this and many other victories graunted vnto vs, and be it his bleſſed will to continue the ſame, and to bleſſe all our lawful enterpriſes, to the praiſe, honor, and glorie of his holy name, and the ſaluation of our ſoules.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Peruſed by me Garret Iohnſon Cater.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2760:4"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
